Guide to the William A. Speck Collection of Goetheana: Manuscripts
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
William A. Speck collection of Goetheana: manuscripts
1542-1967
1770-1900
YCGL MSS 6
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
14.22
(20 boxes) + 41 volumes
The collection, a part of the William A. Speck Collection of Goetheana, consists of correspondence, documents, playscripts, and other writings by or relating to Goethe and his work. The major strength of the manuscript collection is its documentation of Goethe's literary reception in England and America in the nineteenth century. There are 25 letters and manuscripts in Goethe's hand, and several Faust-related items. Authors represented prominently besides Goethe include Thomas Carlyle, Frank Claudy, Samuel Taylor Coleridge, the Faust collector Georg Ehrhardt, Walther Wolfgang von Goethe, August Heinrich Hoffmann von Fallersleben, University of Illinois professor Julius Goebel, Anna Jameson, Johann Caspar Lavater, Friederich von Müller, Henry Crabb Robinson, Friedrich Schiller, Carl Frederick Schreiber, Horatio Robinson Storer, Bayard Taylor, Marie (Hansen) Taylor, Karl August Ludwig Philipp Varnhagen von Ense, and Albert Wünsch.
Other Storage Formats: 41 Bound Volumes, Oversize
Speck, William A. (William Alfred), 1864-1928
Goethe, Johann Wolfgang von, 1749-1832 ( Faust)
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of William A. Speck, 1913, and augmented by several other gifts and purchases.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Associated Materials
Printed works from the Speck Collection are cataloged separately. Two groups of manuscript material, which traditionally have been considered part of the Speck manuscript collection, also are cataloged separately: the William A. Speck Collection of Goetheana: Music (YCGL MSS 9), and the papers of Alice Raphael, Goethe translator, author, and a personal friend of William Speck.
WILLIAM A. SPECK (1864-1928) and THE SPECK COLLECTION OF GOETHEANA
The son of German immigrants, William A. Speck began life in New York City in 1864. His father, Otto Speck, owned an apothecary shop, first in the City, then in Haverstraw, New York, a small community on the Hudson. As a boy, Speck attended Hoboken Academy, a school run largely by Germans, and afterwards earned a degree in chemistry from the Pharmaceutical College of the City of New York. For the next thirty years, Speck conscientiously worked as a druggist in the family business, despite the fact that his real interest lay elsewhere.
Life as a Haverstraw pharmacist allowed Speck ample time to pursue his true passion: Goethe. The New York City antiquarian bookshops were only a day's trip away, and Speck was able to make two European journeys during these years. The destination was, of course, Weimar, where Speck went from door to door, up and down the streets, looking for Goethe relics, buying pictures from inn-keepers, and often gaining access to private collections.
After more than two decades of collecting, Speck saw that his books belonged in an academic setting. Personal ties suggested Columbia as the recipient of the collection; but it was Yale, having heard of the marvelous Goethe museum on the banks of the Hudson, that sent a delegation to visit Speck in 1912. In March, 1913, the Yale Corporation announced that the Goethe Collection, which then numbered about 6,000 items, had been deposited in New Haven, and that Speck had been appointed its curator.
Between the time of Speck's appointment and his death in 1928, the Collection, benefitting from University support, trebled in size. While World War I cut off the source of acquisitions for a time, the 1920s saw the purchase of two major private collections, as well as a steady stream of smaller purchases from dealers around the world. During the last years of his life, Speck was appointed lecturer in the Yale Graduate School, where he offered a course called "Goethe's Personality and Personal Appearance." Publishing relatively little, Speck devoted himself instead to assiduous collecting, firm in his belief that Goethe was "one of the corner-stones ... of our moral world."
The William A. Speck Collection of Goetheana, now the largest Goethe collection outside Germany, contains over 10,000 printed volumes and as many pamphlets, scores, programs, broadsides, prints, art works, and Goethe-related ephemera, as well as the extensive holdings of literary manuscripts, which are described in depth in this finding aid, and of manuscript music, listed and classified separately as YCGL MSS 9.
For a fuller description of the contents and collecting history of the Speck Collection, consult the Guide to the Beinecke collections (New Haven, 1974 and 1994).
Related manuscript sources in the Yale Collection of German Literature include the papers of Karl Gottfried Theodor Winkler (Theodor Hell), Dresden theater director and journalist, who corresponded with many literary figures of Goethe's time. The George Eliot Papers in the Beinecke Library's General Collection of Rare Books and Manuscripts contain much material by and relating to Goethe's biographer George Henry Lewes; some of this material was originally part of the Speck Collection.
Scope and Contents
The major strength of the Speck Collection is its documentation of Goethe's literary reception in England and America in the nineteenth century. The literary manuscript component of the Collection, listed in detail in this finding aid, includes correspondence, documents, playscripts, and other writings. Among the better-known items to be mentioned in this connection are the full draft of Bayard Taylor's translation of Faust (folder 716), translations by George Borrow (folders 225-227), and John Greenleaf Whittier's manuscript for his translation of the poem "Erlkoenig" (folder 249). Translations, criticism, and correspondence about theater productions and the publication of Goethe's works, especially in Great Britain, include letters and manuscripts by such figures as Sarah Austin, Samuel Taylor Coleridge, Margaret Fuller, Richard Graves, Anna Jameson, Charles Kean, and Edward George Bulwer-Lytton.
The manuscripts are arranged alphabetically by author or by title, if the author is unknown. Authors represented prominently include Goethe himself, Thomas Carlyle, Frank Claudy, the Faust collector Georg Ehrhardt, Walther Wolfgang von Goethe, August Heinrich Hoffmann von Fallersleben, University of Illinois professor Julius Goebel, Anna Jameson, Johann Caspar Lavater, Friedrich von Mueller, Henry Crabb Robinson, Friedrich Schiller, Carl Frederick Schreiber, Horatio Robinson Storer, Bayard Taylor, Marie (Hansen) Taylor, Karl August Ludwig Philipp Varnhagen von Ense, and Albert Wuensch. The Rilke manuscripts, chiefly letters to F. A. Huenich (folder 565) and Clotilde Sacharoff (folders 567-568), came into the collection by historical accident and are unrelated to Goethe.
Despite his persistence and the financial resources provided by Yale, Speck could not gather a large number of Goethe autographs, which were already in the great collections at Weimar and Frankfurt and in the Kippenberg Collection. The Speck Collection does, however, include some 25 letters and manuscripts in Goethe's hand, among them the poem "Den funfzehn englischen Freunden" (folder 254), sent in thanks to the group of British writers who, at the suggestion of Thomas Carlyle, had presented Goethe with a gold and enamel seal for his 81st birthday. Goethe's fair copy of the scene "Offene Gegend" from the second part of Faust is another treasure (folder 224). There are in addition many letters to Goethe, and letters from Goethe in secretarial hands. Among the other, related correspondence in the collection are many letters to Johann Peter Eckermann, including seven from Thomas Carlyle (folders 50-56).
The manuscript collection (both literary and music) is particularly strong in Faust-related materials, including two eighteenth-century Hoellenzwang manuscripts, bound, (folders 797-798) and a number of late nineteenth century handwritten copies of Faust puppet plays. There are also several manuscripts by the Swiss theologian Johann Kaspar Lavater, a branch of whose family migrated to Connecticut and became Yale benefactors.
Authors, German -- Archives; Carlyle, Thomas, 1795-1881; Claudy, Frank, 1844-1919; Coleridge, Samuel Taylor, 1772-1834; Ehrhardt, Georg, b. 1862; Goebel, Julius, 1857-1931; Goethe, Johann Wolfgang von, 1749-1832; Goethe, Walther Wolfgang von, 1818-1885; Hoffmann von Fallersleben, August Heinrich, 1798-1874; Jameson, Mrs. (Anna), 1794-1860; Lavater, Johann Caspar, 1741-1801; Müller, Friedrich von, 1779-1849; Robinson, Henry Crabb, 1775-1867; Schiller, Friedrich, 1759-1805; Schreiber, Carl F. (Carl Frederick), 1886-1960; Speck, William A. (William Alfred), 1864-1928; Storer, Horatio Robinson, 1830-1922; Taylor, Bayard, 1825-1878; Taylor, Marie Hansen, 1829-1925; Varnhagen von Ense, Karl August, 1785-1858; Wünsch, Albert
- Box and Folder List, 1542-1967; 7.51; (18 boxes)
  Scope and Contents
  Box and Folder List contains material arranged
  alphabetically under author or title.
  - ACHARD, MARCEL, 1899-1974
    I know my love. A comedy in three
    acts, adapted by N. S. Behrman. [195-?]
    - 1 p. l., 57 l.; 29 cm. Carbon copy of typescript. The second scene of the second act contains Werther references.
    - See: Bound Volumes, folder 790
  - AGRIPPA VON NETTESHEIM, HEINRICH CORNELIUS
    Dates: 1486?-1535
    La Clavicule magique et cabalistique du
    Roy Salomon, avec les pentacules
    talismns, invocations, conjurations des
    esprits célestes. 1732
    - AMs, 1 p. l., 305, 4 p. diagrs.; 23 cm. Title within border of leaf garlands, with the Zodiac at bottom. "Traduit du texte original hebraique en latin par le scauant négromancien Corneille Agrippa, et mise en françois par le Raby Nazar, chef de la Société de la grande Cabale de la Ville d'Arte ... le tout exactement copié sur l'original qui est conservé dans la Bibliothèque de Florence, l'année 1732." Note on p. 1. Bound in full red crushed morocco, both covers gilt tooled, with fleurons, spine compartmented (6), heavily gilt, all edges gilt.
    - See: Bound Volumes, folder 791
  - AHLEFELD, CHARLOTTE (VON SEEBACH) VON, 1781-1849
    - ALS: Weimar, to Ferdinand Ludwig Karl, Freiherr von Biedenfeld, [1837?] (Box 1, Folder 1)
      1 p.; 13 x 18 cm.
      C. Ahlefeld, authoress writing under
      the pseud. Elise Selbig.
  - ALICKE, PAUL
    - Publication contract, signed, Dresden, 1904 Nov 11
      - 1 p.; 30 cm. On stationery "Wissenschaftliches Antiquariat Paul Alicke." Contract between Georg Ehrhardt and Paul Alicke, signed by both, for publication of Ehrhardt's edition of Faust puppet-play, 1905.
      - IN: Faust puppet-play Box 4, folders 153-153a.
    - 3 Postcards, signed: Dresden, to Georg Ehrhardt, 1904 Nov 20
      - 1905 Nov 4 Third postcard undated. Concerning Ehrhardt's edition of Faust puppet-play edition of 1905.
      - IN: Faust puppet-play Box 4, folders 153-153a.
    - ALS, to Georg Ehrhardt, 1904 Nov 27
      - 1 p.; 18 cm. Concerning use of two colors for title page of Ehrhardt's edition of Faust puppet-play, 1905.
      - IN: Faust puppet-play, Box 4, folders 153-153a.
  - ANDREWS, WILLIAM PAGE, 1848-1916
    - ALS: Capri, Italy, to Prof. Gustav Gruener, 1913 Mar 30 (Box 1, Folder 2)
      2 p.; 20 x 25 cm.
      Announcing dispatch of a copy of his
      Goethe's Key to Faust.
  - ANNA AMALIA, DUCH. OF SAXE-WEIMAR-EISENACH, 1739-1807
    - Document, signed: Weimar, to the Administration of Eisenach, 1771 Nov 29 (Box 1, Folder 3)
      2 p.; 22 x 23 cm.
      Official impressed seal attached.
      Concerning filling of a vacancy in
      the "March-Commissarien Stelle."
  - APEL, HEINRICH
    - Götz von Berlichingen mit der eisernen Hand (Box 1, Folder 4)
      AMs, 115 p.; 21 x 17 cm.
      Puppet-play in 4 acts.
      Contains 12 pictures.
      Title on label pasted on cover.
  - ARNDT, ERNST MORITZ, 1769-1860
    - Autograph poem, signed, "Schau die Welt wie ein Vogel da oben," Bonn, 1850 Jul 2 (Box 1, Folder 5)
      1 p.; 13 x 21 cm.
      Printed in his Gedichte
      vollständige Sammlung, Berlin,
      1860, p. 635.
  - ARNOLD, MATTHEW, 1822-1888
    - ALS: Cobham, Surrey, to Messrs. Nutt, 1885 Dec 24 (Box 1, Folder 6)
      1 p.; 18 x 12 cm.
      Letter declines invitation to join
      Goethe Society.
      Official impressed seal: Education
      Department Whitehall.
  - ARNTZ, MRS. MARTHA
    - AL: London?, to J. Wright, Esq., 1830 Nov 24 (Box 1, Folder 7)
      1 p.; 11 x 18 cm.
      Personal black seal attached.
  - AUERSWALD, FRANZ
    - ALS: Börnchen, Bezirk Dresden, to Georg Ehrhardt, 1902 Sep 24
      - 3 p.; 18 cm. Announcing shipment of Pirrinet's text of the Faust puppet-play.
      - IN: Faust puppet-play, Bound Volumes, folder 800.
  - AUSTIN, MRS. SARAH (TAYLOR), 1793-1867
    - ALS: Bayswater near London, to "Gentlemen", 1834 Jan 6 (Box 1, Folder 8)
      4 p.; 11 x 19 cm.
      Apparently directed to a German
      publishing house, which had
      requested her to translate a volume
      of correspondence. She explains her
      unwillingness; her "work on Goethe
      [Characteristics of Goethe, London,
      1833] has [not] had a sufficient
      sale to encourage me much ... Need
      I say they [the public] complain
      that Goethe is obscure."
  - BAGINSKY, PAUL, B. 1896
    - Des jungen Goethe Lektüre während der Frankfurter Jugendzeit, [Breslau], [1919] (Box 1, Folder 9)
      Typescript (carbon), xxi, 74 l.
      32 cm.
      "Literaturverzeichnis": l. vii-xii.
  - BAHRDT, KARL FRIEDRICH, 1741-1792
    - Autograph quotation in Greek, Giessen, 1772 Feb 1 (Box 1, Folder 10)
      1 p.; 10 x 16 cm.
      The last part of the 11th verse of
      Galatians III, "The just shall live
      by faith."
      Signed: D. Carolus Friedricus Bahrdt.
      Apparently p. 7-8 of an autograph
      album.
  - BAILEY, PHILIP JAMES, 1816-1902
    - From "Festus", n.d. (Box 1, Folder 11)
      1 p.; 12 x 18 cm.
      Autograph quotation, signed Philip
      Jas Bailey.
      The first line of the Ms appears in
      the Proëm of the 1845 edition of
      his "Festus" (p. xiii); the
      remainder differs from the book.
  - BANCROFT, GEORGE, 1800-1891
    - ALS: Berlin, to Bayard Taylor, 1872 Jul 26 (Box 1, Folder 12)
      4 p.; 11 x 18 cm.
  - BANFIELD, THOMAS COLLINS
    - ALS: Vienna, to Prof. Friedrich Wilhelm Riemer, 1832 Feb 15 (Box 1, Folder 13)
      3 p.; 21 x 26 cm.
      Small slip attached, 1 p.; 6 x
      13 cm.
      Red and black personal seal attached.
  - BARTSCH, KARL FRIEDRICH, 1832-1888
    - An dem Tage, da der Weggefährte, 1880 Oct 12 (Box 1, Folder 14)
      1 p.; 11 x 17 cm.
      Autograph poem, signed: K. B.
      Printed in Philological Quarterly,
      v. V, no. 2.
      J. F. L. Raschen found this poem
      written on verso of cover title
      of Wanderung und Heimkehr.
      Gedichte von Karl Bartsch, Leipzig,
      1874.
  - BATSCH, AUGUST JOHANN GEORG KARL, 1761-1802
    - ALS: Jena, to "Ew. Hoch Edelgebohren", 1798 Apr 15 (Box 1, Folder 15)
      2 p.; 5 x 19 cm.
  - BATTY, GEORGE, D. 1821
    - Autograph receipt, signed: Weimar, to Grossherzoglich Weimar- Eisenachische Cammer, 1817 Dec 10 (Box 1, Folder 16)
      1 p.; 20 x 17 cm.
  - BAUERNFELD, EDUARD VON, 1802-1890
    - Wie deutsch der alte Goethe war, 1847 (Box 1, Folder 17)
      Autograph poem, signed: Bauernfeld.
      Four lines, apparently a leaf from
      an autograph album.
  - BAYERISCHER RUNDFUNK, MÜNCHEN
    - Aus Briefen und Tagebüchern; Begegnungen mit Goethe, 1954 Aug (Box 1, Folder 18)
      22 l.; 30 cm.
      Typescript, mimeographed.
  - BERLICHINGEN, GÖTZ VON, 1480-1562
    - Letter to the Councillors of Würzburg, 1542 Oct 3 (Box 1, Folder 19)
      1 p., with address.
      "The knight of the iron hand," the
      German hero about whom Goethe
      wrote his play, Götz von
      Berlichingen.
      Requesting to delay the matter of
      certain fiefs which he and his
      brothers were to receive.
      Body of letter and signature in the
      handwriting of a secretary.
      Given in honor of Curt von Faber du
      Faur by Herman W. Liebert, October
      1958.
  - BERLIOZ, HECTOR, 1803-1869
    - Nature immense, impénétrable et fière, Hartzburg, 1853 Oct 28 (Box 1, Folder 20)
      AMs, signed, 1 p.; 17 x 23 cm.
      "Invocation à la nature, fragment de
      La damnation de Faust" in 11 lines.
      The leaf appears to be from an
      autograph album; on the verso are
      signatures of ten different people,
      two poems, and illustrations
      German text is in German script.
  - BERNAYS, ADOLPHUS, D. 1864
    - ALS: London, to Dr. Johann Peter Eckermann, 1839 Nov 28 (Box 1, Folder 21)
      4 p.; 18 x 23 cm.
      Announcing the dispatch of a copy of
      the English translation of Goethe's
      Faust, Pt. 2, done by his son,
      Leopold John Bernays, and asking for
      an evaluation of it.
  - BERTLING, K. O.
    - Goettingen und die U.S.A. Zur 200- Jahrfeier der Georg-August Universität in Göttingen. (23.-30. Juni 1937) (Box 1, Folder 22)
      7 numb. l.; 30 cm.
      Typescript (mimeographed copy)
  - BERTUCH, FRIEDRICH JUSTIN, 1747-1822
    - ALS: Weimar, to Georg Joachim Göschen, 1786 Jul 25 (Box 1, Folder 23)
      Concerns chiefly the publication of
      the Göschen edition of Goethe's
      collected works.
    - ALS: Weimar, to Georg Joachim Göschen, 1796 Sep 20 (Box 1, Folder 24)
      1 p.; 11 x 19 cm.
  - BILLE, THEKLA
    - ALS: Wolfsheim, to Max Kirmse, 1913 May 28
      - 2 p.; 22 cm. Concerning Kirmse's application for position with her theatre; cannot loan puppet-play text.
      - IN: Faust puppet-play, box 4, folder 159.
  - BINCKES, HENRY ASHBEY
    Faust, an opera by Henry Ashbey
    Binckes, London. 1867
    - AMs, 4 p. l., 103 l. front. (port.); 26 x 21 cm. A parody adaptation of Goethe's Faust in verse; without music; stage directions indicate popular tunes, to which some of the poems are to be sung, accompanied by band or orchestra. Title in red and black calligraphy; the word "Faust" embellished with human figures representing characters in the play; names of characters and stage directions in red, all within red line borders. The frontispiece is a photograph of the author, with his signature below. Bound in half leather. With: Song, "Come let us be jovial," by H. A. B., 3 l. following l. 103. Within black borders.
    - See: Bound Volumes, folder 792
  - BISHOP, SIR HENRY ROWLEY, 1786-1855
    - ALS: Hyde Park, London, to Charles John Kean, 1854 May 31 (Box 1, Folder 25)
      Bishop, the English composer of
      operas, glees, and songs,
      compliments the actor, Kean, on
      his interpretation of
      Mephistopheles in the London
      production of Goethe's Faust.
  - BODE, JOHANN JOACHIM CHRISTOPH, 1730-1793
    - ALS: Weimar, to "Mein liebster Freund" [Leipzig], 1788 May 2 (Box 1, Folder 26)
      2 p.; 19 x 23 cm.
      Bode came to Weimar in 1778, where he
      became a member of the circle of
      the Grandduchess Anna Amalia. An
      enthusiastic Mason, he had the
      pleasure of inducting both Grandduke
      Karl August and Goethe into the
      Lodge Anna Amalia. Translator of
      Goldsmith, Smollett, and Fielding.
  - BODMER, HENRIETTE
    - 2 autograph poems, charades: "Dreÿ Sÿlben geb ich dir", solution: Lavater; "Mein Erster ist ein Fluss", solution: Licht-Escher, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 27)
      3 p.; 12 x 10 cm.
      On p. 4: Die vorstehende Charade ist
      von Mademoiselle Henriette Bodmer im
      Wind-Egg componiert, einer Enklin
      von Herr Escher v.d.L.
      All, incl. the note on p. 4, in the
      same unidentified handwriting.
      Removed from Lavater, Johann Caspar:
      Erwekkungs-Predigt, Zürich, 1798.
  - BÖHLAU, CHRISTOPH DIETRICH VON, 1707-1750
    - An der Frau Geheimbden Legations Räthin von Wollzogin Gnaden
      - 8 line poem in ms. Signed: "Womit sich zu unablässlichem gnädigen Andenken empfiehlt Der Verfasser." On front fly-leaf.
      - IN: Böhlau, Christoph Dietrich von. Poetische Jugend-Früchte. Coburg und Leipzig [1740] 20 cm. (Zg17B61 740)
  - BOISSERÉE, SULPIZ, 1783-1854
    - ALS: Bonn, to Emilio Braun, 1848 Oct 28 (Box 1, Folder 28)
      1 p.; 14 x 22 cm.
      Introducing a young sculptor named
      Kauer from Kreuznach who is on his
      way to Rome.
    - ALS: Köln, to Cotta'sche Druckerei Anstalt, 1841 Sep 30 (Box 1, Folder 29)
      1 p.; 22 x 27 cm.
      Notice that he has sent 22 leaves of
      his "Die Denkmäler der Baukunst am
      Niederrhein", a second edition of
      which appeared in 1842.
  - BONESKY, RICHARD, B. 1867
    - ALS: Setzschkau i.L., to Georg Ehrhardt, [1904?] Dec 17
      - 2 p.; 18 cm. Announcing shipment of theatre bills and promising old puppet-play textbooks.
      - IN: Faust puppet-play, box 4, folders 153-153a.
  - BORROW, GEORGE, 1803-1881
    - Chrimehilt, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 30)
      Autograph poem, 4 p.; 18 x 22 cm.
      English translation of the opening
      Canto of the Nibelungenlied.
      Version in blank verse.
      Typewritten copy enclosed.
    - Chrimehilt, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 31)
      Autograph poem, 4 p.; 22 x 28 cm.
      Nineteen stanzas in rhyme.
      Mr. Wise made Mr. Speck a present of
      several Borrow mss. These may have
      been among them.
  - BRANDEGEE, EMILY S.
    - A brief record of the meeting of Lord Byron and Mrs. Catherine Potter Stith, by her granddaughter, Emily S. Brandegee (Box 1, Folder 32)
      AMs, 2 l.; 25 x 20 cm.
  - BRAUN, AUGUST EMIL, 1809-1856
    - ALS: Dresden, to Johann Peter Eckermann, 1832 Nov 23 (Box 1, Folder 33)
      2 p.; 21 x 25 cm.
    - ALS: Dresden, to Verlagsbuchhandlung des Herrn Fleischer, 1832 Nov 12 (Box 1, Folder 34)
      2 p.; 20 x 23 cm.
      Personal red seal attached.
  - BROWN, REBECCA WARREN
    - ALS: New Haven, Conn.?, to Mrs. Eli Whitney, 1878 Dec
      - 2 p.; 12 x 9 cm. With envelope. Mrs. R. W. Brown was the author of the explanatory text to the Goethe gallery, a dedicated copy of which she was sending to Mrs. Whitney.
      - IN: Kaulbach, Wilhelm von. The Goethe gallery. Boston & Cambridge, 1879. (Ck9 +879k copy 2)
  - BRYANT, WILLIAM CULLEN, 1794-1878
    - ALS: Roslyn, Long Island, N.Y., to "My dear Sir", 1875 Nov 17 (Box 1, Folder 35)
      1 p.; 12 x 20 cm.
      "I know nothing whatever of the
      subscription to a fund for the
      proposed bust of Goethe. I have
      never subscribed a hundred dollars
      and the use of my name to which you
      refer is wholly unauthorized."
  - BÜRGER, GOTTFRIED AUGUST, 1747-1794
    - ALS: Altengleichen?, to Johann Christian Dieterich, 1778 Mar 26 (Box 1, Folder 36)
      1 p.; 20 x 33 cm.
      With address: An Herrn Buchhändler
      Dietrich in Göttingen.
  - BUSONI, FERRUCCIO BENVENUTO, 1866-1924
    - Doctor Faust. Poem and Music (Box 1, Folder 37)
      34 l.; 30 cm.
      Typescript (original), with some ms.
      corr. by the translator.
      Translation, by Lydia Marion Fuehr, of
      Busoni's Doktor Faust, Dichtung und
      Musik, 1925.
      With a printed German text (Leipzig:
      Breitkopf & Härtel, 1925), with
      copious ms. notes by the translator.
      Accompanied by an ALS from the
      translator to F. H. Bangs, Berlin,
      Feb. 10, 1932, 4 p., presenting him
      with the translation and the
      annotated printed version of the
      original.
  - BYRON, GEORGE GORDON NOEL BYRON, 6TH BAR. 1788-1824
    - ALS, to Major Townshend Stith (Box 1, Folder 38)
      1 p.
      Mounted on sheet with address: To Mrs.
      Stith, &c. &c. &c.
      Signed: N. B.
      Printed in Benson, A. B., Catherine
      Potter Stith and her meeting with
      Lord Byron, in South Atlantic
      Quarterly, v. 22, 1923.